TED：你应该相信你的第一印象吗？
Should you trust your first impression
Imagine you're at a football game
想象你在看一场足球赛
when this obnoxious guy sits next to you.
旁边坐着一个讨厌鬼
He's loud,
他讲话很大声
he spills his drink on you,
饮料洒到你
and he makes fun of your team.
他还嘲笑你支持的球队
Days later, you're walking in the park
几天之后，你在公园散步
when suddenly it starts to pour rain.
突然下了一场大雨
Who should show up at your side
谁应该出现在你身旁
to offer you an umbrella?
给你一把雨伞呢？
The same guy from the football game.
就是足球赛那个讨厌鬼
Do you change your mind about him
你会改变你对他的印象吗？
based on this second encounter,
根据你们第二次相遇
or do you go with your first impression
还是你依旧相信你的第一印象
and write him off?
Research in social psychology suggests
社会心理学的研究指出
that we're quick to form lasting impressions of others
我们很快就能对他人产生长久印象
based on their behaviors.
依据他人的行为
We manage to do this with little effort,
我们很自然就这么做
inferring stable character traits
从单一行为举止
from a single behavior,
推论出长久的人格特质
like a harsh word
像是说了脏话
or a clumsy step.
或是犯了很傻的错误
Using our impressions as guides,
我们用印象做为指引
we can accurately predict
能够准确的预测
how people are going to behave in the future.
这些人在未来会有什么样的举止
Armed with the knowledge
有了这种知识
the guy from the football game
足球比赛的那个家伙
was a jerk the first time you met him,
你第一次遇见他，觉得他是个混蛋
you might expect more of the same down the road.
你可能会觉得他以后也是个混蛋
If so, you might choose to avoid him
要是这样，如果下一次你看到他
the next time you see him.
你会选择避开他
That said, we can change our impressions
换言之，我们会改变印象
in light of new information.
因为我们得到新的信息
Behavioral researchers have identified
行为研究员指出
consistent patterns that seem to guide
这种持续模式似乎会引导着
this process of impression updating.
我们处理印象的方向
On one hand, learning very negative,
一方面，知道关于某人非常负面
highly immoral information about someone
非常不道德的信息
typically has a stronger impact
基本上会有更强的影响
than learning very positive, highly moral information.
相对于得知某人有非常正面、道德的信息
So, unfortunately for our new friend
所以，我们足球场的新朋友
from the football game,
很不幸的
his bad behavior at the game
他在球场的坏行为
might outweigh his good behavior at the park.
可能比他在公园的好行为还要强烈
Research suggests that this bias occurs
研究指出之所以有这种偏见
because immoral behaviors are more diagnostic,
是因为从不道德的行为就能见微知着
or revealing,
或是能比较真实
of a person's true character.
显露出一个人真正的个性
Okay, so by this logic,
好，依据这样的逻辑
bad is always stronger than good
当有新的印象出现时
when it comes to updating.
坏的效果比好的效果来得强烈
Well, not necessarily.
不过，也不尽然如此
Certain types of learning don't seem to lead
特定几种的学习似乎并不会
to this sort of negativity bias.
导向这种负面偏见
When learning about another person's abilities and competencies,
举例来说
for instance,
this bias flips.
这偏见就完全不相同
It's actually the positive information
事实上这种正面的信息
that gets weighted more heavily.
会来得更重要
Let's go back to that football game.
让我们再回到足球场
If a player scores a goal,
足球员射门得分
it ultimately has a stronger impact
这最后会有个更强的影响
on your impression of their skills
加深你对他们球技的印象
than if they miss the net.
比起他们没有得分的话
The two sides of the updating story
这两种改变印象的故事
are ultimately quite consistent.
在最后都满有关联性
Overall, behaviors that are perceived
总的来说
as being less frequent are also the ones
在形成以及更新印象时
that people tend to weigh more heavily
人们对不太常出现的行为
when forming and updating impressions,
印象会比较深刻
highly immoral actions
或是非常不道德的行为
and highly competent actions.
还有非常令人满意的行为的时候
So, what's happening at the level of the brain
所以，当大脑在更新印象的时候
when we're updating our impressions?
这中间到底发生了什么事？
Using fMRI,
透过 fMRI
or functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging,
也就是功能性磁振造影
researchers have identified
研究员指出
an extended network of brain regions
有一块大脑区域延伸出的网络
that respond to new information
对于和第一印象不同的
that's inconsistent with initial impressions.
新信息会有反应
These include areas typically associated
这些区块基本上都和
with social cognition,
社会认知
attention,
注意力
and cognitive control.
以及认知控制有关
Moreover, when updating impressions
此外，更新印象的时候
based on people's behaviors,
若是以行为做基础
activity in the ventrolateral prefrontal cortex
在腹侧前额叶皮质区
and the superior temporal sulcus
以及上侧颞叶沟的活动
correlates with perceptions
和我们所认为
of how frequently those behaviors occur in daily life.
那些行为在生活中出现的频率有关
In other words, the brain seems to be tracking
换言之，大脑似乎会根据
low-level, statistical properties of behavior
统计中较低机率的行为特征
in order to make complex decisions
针对他人的个性
regarding other people's character.
做出复杂的决定
It needs to decide
大脑需要决定
is this person's behavior typical
这个人的行为合乎常理吗？
or is it out of the ordinary?
还是违背常理？
In the situation
在那个情况
with the obnoxious-football-fan-turned-good-samaritan,
讨厌的足球迷最后成了好心人
your brain says,
你的大脑说：
"Well, in my experience,
「嗯，根据我的经验
pretty much anyone would lend someone their umbrella,
很多人都可以借别人雨伞
but the way this guy acted at the football game,
但是这个人在足球场的举止
that was unusual."
却只有他会这样。」
And so, you decide to go with your first impression.
所以，你还是决定相信第一印象
There's a good moral in this data:
有个不错的道德故事和这资料有关：
your brain, and by extension you,
你的大脑，延伸出去就是你
might care more about
会比较在乎
the very negative, immoral things
另一个人所做的非常负面
another person has done
非常不道德的事情
compared to the very positive, moral things,
而非十分正面且道德的事
but it's a direct result
但这个直接的结果
of the comparative rarity of those bad behaviors.
存在于相对及少数的坏行为之中
We're more used to people being basically good,
我们比较习惯他人友善
like taking time to help a stranger in need.
像是找时间去帮助需要的人
In this context, bad might be stronger than good,
这种情况下，坏行为比好行为更强烈
but only because good is more plentiful.
只是因为好行为占多数
Think about the last time you judged someone
想一下你上一次根据他人行为
based on their behavior,
而评断某人的时候
especially a time when you really feel
尤其是当你真心觉得
like you changed your mind about someone.
你想改变你对某人印象的时候
Was the behavior that caused you
那种让你会
to update your impression
改变印象的行为
something you'd expect anyone to do,
是你认为大家都能做的
or was it something totally out of the ordinary?
还是只有少数人才会做的？